<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>buddhavacana – Documentation</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/</link><description>Recent content in Documentation on buddhavacana</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Pali</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/pali/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/pali/</guid><description>
&lt;dl>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://palistudies.blogspot.com">LEARN PALI LANGUAGE&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Pali language grammar tutorials. Learn to read the Pali language for yourself. This blog is to help those wishing to make a first stab at translating the Pāli language &amp;amp; scriptures.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.baus.org/en/teaching/learning-pali/">Learning Pali – Buddha’s Language&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Buddhist Association of the United States.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://bodhimonastery.org/a-course-in-the-pali-language.html">A Course in the Pali Language&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>This course is designed to help you to learn the basics of Pali grammar and vocabulary through direct study of selections from the Buddha’s discourses. It thus aims to enable you to read the Buddha’s discourses in the original as quickly as possible. The textbook for the course is A New Course in Reading Pali: Entering the Word of the Buddha by James Gair and W.S. Karunatilleke (1998, Motilal Banarsidass Publishers, Delhi, India. ISBN 81-208-1440-1). The Pali grammatical tables were designed by Bhikkhu Nyanatusita.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://ocbs-courses.org">OCBS Courses&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Online Courses from the Oxford Centre for Buddhist Studies&lt;/dd>
&lt;/dl></description></item><item><title>Docs: Tipitaka</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/tipitaka/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/tipitaka/</guid><description>
&lt;dl>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net">SuttaCentral&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>SuttaCentral contains early Buddhist texts, known as the Tipiṭaka or “Three Baskets”. This is a large collection of teachings attributed to the Buddha or his earliest disciples, who were teaching in India around 2500 years ago. They are regarded as sacred canon in all schools of Buddhism.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.ancient-buddhist-texts.net">Ancient Buddhist Texts&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Materials from the early and medieval Buddhist tradition covering texts in Pāli and Sanskrit; line by line (interlinear) texts and translations; translations in English only; studies of grammar, prosody and compilation; maps, reference works and audio files.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://tipitaka.org">Pali Tipitaka&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>This web site is based on the Chaṭṭha Saṅgāyana CD published by the Vipassana Research Institute. Based at Dhamma Giri, Igatpuri, near Mumbai, India, the Vipassana Research Institute also publishes literature &amp;amp; disseminates information related to Vipassana Meditation Technique as taught by S.N.Goenka in the tradition of Sayagyi U Ba Khin.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://tipitaka.app">Tipitaka.app&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Tipitaka.app is a free software built and distributed as a Dhamma donation. It will always be free and a property of the Buddhist World.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.accesstoinsight.org">Access to Insight&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Access to Insight is an HTML website dedicated to providing accurate, reliable, and useful information concerning the practice and study of Theravada Buddhism, as it has been handed down to us through both the written word of the Pali canon and the living example of the Sangha.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sltp/index.html">Sri Lanka Tripitaka Project&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Sri Lanka Tripitaka Project is a public domain electronic version of the Pali Canon.&lt;/dd>
&lt;/dl></description></item><item><title>Docs: Websites</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/websites/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/websites/</guid><description>
&lt;dl>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.dhammacharts.org">DhammaCharts&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Buddhist Association of the United States ® (BAUS) is a non-denominational organization dedicated to promoting the Buddha’s teachings in the United States. Founded in 1964 by a group of devout Chinese Buddhists living in the greater New York area, BAUS offers a wide range of programs, including weekly Dharma classes, meditation retreats, and traditional religious rituals. Although rooted in the Chinese Buddhist tradition, BAUS does not represent any particular school of Buddhism, nor is it is affiliated with any other Buddhist organization. BAUS adopts a broad perspective on the Buddha’s teachings, and thus hosts programs by qualified teachers from all genuine Buddhist traditions, both Theravada and Mahayana.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.baus.org/en/">Buddhist Association of the United States&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Buddhist Association of the United States ® (BAUS) is a non-denominational organization dedicated to promoting the Buddha’s teachings in the United States. Founded in 1964 by a group of devout Chinese Buddhists living in the greater New York area, BAUS offers a wide range of programs, including weekly Dharma classes, meditation retreats, and traditional religious rituals. Although rooted in the Chinese Buddhist tradition, BAUS does not represent any particular school of Buddhism, nor is it is affiliated with any other Buddhist organization. BAUS adopts a broad perspective on the Buddha’s teachings, and thus hosts programs by qualified teachers from all genuine Buddhist traditions, both Theravada and Mahayana.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://bodhimonastery.org">Bodhi Monastery&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Bodhi Monastery is a distinctive Buddhist monastery located in the rolling hills of Sussex County, New Jersey. Set on 188 acres of verdant woodlands and fields, amidst herds of deer, the monastery offers a fresh yet ancient perspective on the practice of Buddhism in today’s world. The origins of Bodhi Monastery lie in the comprehensive, non–sectarian vision of Master Yin–Shun, the foremost Chinese scholar–monk of modern times, whose work has inspired a Buddhist intellectual renaissance in Taiwan. In line with the vision of Master Yin–Shun, Bodhi Monastery aims to promote the study and practice of Buddhism as an integral whole rather than to focus on the teachings of a particular Buddhist sect or branch.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.bps.lk">Buddhist Publication Society&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Buddhist Publication Society (BPS), founded in Sri Lanka in 1958, is an approved charity dedicated to making known the teaching of the Buddha. BPS publications generally represent the standpoint of Theravada Buddhism or Southern Buddhism, the oldest living Buddhist tradition of which the Pali Canon gives the most authentic account of what the historical Buddha himself actually taught. In a span of nearly five decades the BPS has become a major Buddhist publisher with hundreds of titles and a field of distribution extending all over the world.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="http://www.buddhanet.net">BuddhaNet&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>BuddhaNet™ is the result of a vision to link up with the growing world-wide culture of people committed to the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s teachings and lifestyle, as an on-line cyber sangha. In this way, an ancient tradition and the information superhighway will come together to create an electronic meeting place of shared concern and interests.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.fgsitc.org">Fo Guang Shan International Translation Center&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Fo Guang Shan International Translation Center is dedicated to translating and distributing quality translations of classical Buddhist texts as well as works by contemporary Buddhist teachers and scholars. We embrace Humanistic Buddhism and promote Buddhist writing that is accessible, community-oriented, and relevant to daily life. You can browse all of our publications, read them online, and even download them for FREE, as well as request printed copies for you or your organization.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="http://buddhasutra.com">BuddhaSutra&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The purpose of this website is to propagate Buddha Dharma to the whole world. As we all know that this is the Dharma-Ending age, Buddhism is getting weaker whereas our worldy desires grow stronger.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://scriptoq.com/page/resources/book_index/buddhism/theravada">Scripto-Q&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Scripto·Q is an e-book library initiative dedicated to making classical texts and commentaries on oriental philosophy and mysticism freely available and accessible in multiple dimensions — for the benefit of enthusiasts and researchers alike.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="http://www.palitext.com">Pali Text Society&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Society was founded in 1881 by T.W. Rhys Davids &amp;ldquo;to foster and promote the study of Pāli texts&amp;rdquo;. It publishes Pāli texts in roman characters, translations in English and ancillary works including dictionaries, a concordance, books for students of Pāli and a journal. Most of the classical texts and commentaries have now been edited and many works translated into English. The Society aims to keep almost all its publications in print and to produce at least two new books and a volume of its Journal each year.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.bodhipaksa.com">Bodhipaksa&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>I’m a Buddhist teacher and author living in New Hampshire, although I’m originally from Scotland.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://alanpeto.com">Alan Peto&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>I’m Alan Peto, and I am passionate about helping beginners and Westerners learn Buddhism through my articles, books, videos and graphics in a way they can understand.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.urbandharma.org/index6.html">Urban Dharma&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>UrbanDharma.org is supported and maintained for the use of anyone and everyone interested in Buddhism.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://www.budsas.org/index.htm">BuddhaSasana&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>A Buddhist Page by Binh Anson.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://obo.genaud.net/index.htm">BuddhaDust&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The site is intended to be adopted by those interested in making the Dhamma their theme for meditation and for Dhamma researchers of all stripes. It is intended as a pattern, to be used as a basis for a personal desktop work environment or as a basis for promoting some view on the web, and should be seen as incomplete, needing correction, revision and improvement in all departments.&lt;/dd>
&lt;/dl></description></item><item><title>Docs: Magazines</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/magazines/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/reference/magazines/</guid><description>
&lt;dl>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://wisdomexperience.org">Wisdom Experience&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Wisdom Publications is the leading publisher of books and online courses on contemporary and classic Buddhism, mindfulness, and meditation. We’re also the premier membership platform for Buddhists, having launched the Wisdom Experience in 2019 and now providing hundreds of hours of video and thousands of pages of books for our members to read online. Additionally, we publish the Wisdom Podcast and the Wisdom Journal.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://tricycle.org">Tricycle&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>Established in 1990 as a nonprofit 501(c)(3) educational organization, The Tricycle Foundation is dedicated to making Buddhist teachings and practices broadly available. In 1991 the Foundation launched Tricycle: The Buddhist Review, the first magazine intended to present Buddhist perspectives to a Western readership. Tricycle soon became the leading independent journal of Buddhism in the West, where it continues to be the most inclusive and widely read vehicle for the dissemination of Buddhist views and values. Our readership includes longtime practitioners, those who are curious about Buddhism or meditation, and those who do not identify as Buddhist but value the teachings of wisdom and compassion that Buddhism has to offer.&lt;/dd>
&lt;dt>&lt;a href="https://blogs.dickinson.edu/buddhistethics/">Journal of Buddhist Ethics&lt;/a>&lt;/dt>
&lt;dd>The Journal of Buddhist Ethics is the first academic journal dedicated entirely to Buddhist ethics. We promote the study of Buddhist ethics through the publication of research and book reviews and by hosting occasional online conferences.&lt;/dd>
&lt;/dl></description></item><item><title>Docs: paṭiccasamuppādaṁ</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/pa%E1%B9%ADiccasamupp%C4%81da%E1%B9%81/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/pa%E1%B9%ADiccasamupp%C4%81da%E1%B9%81/</guid><description>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-mermaid" data-lang="mermaid">stateDiagram-v2
[*] --&amp;gt; avijjā
avijjā --&amp;gt; saṅkhārā
saṅkhārā --&amp;gt; viññāṇaṁ
viññāṇaṁ --&amp;gt; nāmarūpaṁ
nāmarūpaṁ --&amp;gt; saḷāyatanaṁ
saḷāyatanaṁ --&amp;gt; phasso
phasso --&amp;gt; vedanā
vedanā --&amp;gt; taṇhā
taṇhā --&amp;gt; upādānaṁ
upādānaṁ --&amp;gt; bhavo
bhavo --&amp;gt; jāti
jāti --&amp;gt; jarāmaraṇaṁ sokaparidevadukkhadomanassupāyāsā sambhavanti
jarāmaraṇaṁ sokaparidevadukkhadomanassupāyāsā sambhavanti --&amp;gt; [*]
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="reference">Reference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/dn22">Mahāsatipaṭṭhānasutta DN 22 PTS 2.290–2.315 PT&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/mn141">Saccavibhaṅgasutta MN 141 PTS 3.248–3.252&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/pli-tv-kd1">Mahākhandhaka Pli Tv Kd 1 PTS 1.1–1.100 P&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Docs: cattāri ariyasaccāni</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/cattari-ariasaccani/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/cattari-ariasaccani/</guid><description>
&lt;p>dukkham samudayo nirodho magga&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cattāri-ariyasaccāni">cattāri ariyasaccāni&lt;/h2>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># cattāri ariyasaccāni
## idam dukkham
- pain
- incapable of suffering
## ayam dukkha-samudayo
- origin
- arising
## ayam dukkha-nirodha
- cease
- suppress
## ayam dukkha-nirodha-gamini patipada
- leading to
- path, way
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="dukkhasaccaniddesa">Dukkhasaccaniddesa&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="dukkhaṁ-ariyasaccaṁ">dukkhaṁ ariyasaccaṁ&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>noble truth of suffering&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># dukkhā
## jāti
- (re)birth
## jarā
- old age
## maraṇaṁ
- death
## sokaparidevadukkhadomanassupāyāsā
## appiyehi sampayogo
- association with dislikes
## piyehi vippayogo
- separation from loved ones
## yampicchaṁ na labhati tam
- not getting what you want
## pañcupādānakkhandhā
- five grasping aggregates
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap">## jāti
### jāti
- rebirth
### sañjāti
- inception
### okkanti
- conception
### abhinibbatti
- reincarnation
### khandhānaṁ pātubhāvo
- manifestation of the sets of phenomena
### āyatanānaṁ paṭilābho
- acquisition of the sense fields
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap">## jarā
### jarā
- old age
### jīraṇatā
- decrepitude
### khaṇḍiccaṁ
- broken teeth
### pāliccaṁ
- grey hair
### valittacatā
- wrinkly skin
### āyuno saṁhāni
- diminished vitality
### indriyānaṁ paripāko
- failing faculties
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap">## maraṇaṁ
### cuti
- passing away
- perishing
### cavanatā
- demise
- mortality
### bhedo antaradhānaṁ
- disintegration
### maccu
- death
### maraṇaṁ
- decease
### kālakiriyā khandhānaṁ
- breaking up of the aggregates
### bhedo kaḷevarassa
- laying to rest of the corpse
### nikkhepo jīvitindriyassupacchedo
- cutting off of the life faculty
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="pañcupādānakkhandhā">pañcupādānakkhandhā&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>five grasping aggregates&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># pañcupādānakkhandhā
## rūpupādānakkhandho
- form
## vedanupādānakkhandho
- feeling
## saññupādānakkhandho
- perception
## saṅkhārupādānakkhandho
- choices (intentional activities)
## viññāṇupādānakkhandho
- consciousness
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="dukkhasamudayaṁ-ariyasaccaṁ">dukkhasamudayaṁ ariyasaccaṁ&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>noble truth of the origin of suffering&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># dukkhasamudayaṁ ariyasaccaṁ
## yāyaṁ taṇhā ponobbhavikā nandīrāgasahagatā tatratatrābhinandinī
- the craving that leads to rebirth, that comes with delight and sensual desire, ever delighting in this and that
## kāmataṇhā
- craving for worldly pleasures
## bhavataṇhā
- craving for existence
## vibhavataṇhā
- craving for prosperity
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="dukkhanirodhaṁ-ariyasaccaṁ">dukkhanirodhaṁ ariyasaccaṁ&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>noble truth of the cessation of suffering&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># dukkhanirodhaṁ ariyasaccaṁ
## yo tassāyeva taṇhāya asesavirāganirodho
- full fading away and ending of all craving
## cāgo
- giving it up
## paṭinissaggo
- relinquishing it
## mutti
- releasing it
## anālayo
- letting it go
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="dukkhanirodhagāminī-paṭipadā-ariyasaccaṁ">dukkhanirodhagāminī paṭipadā ariyasaccaṁ&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>noble truth of the path leading to the end of suffering&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ariyo aṭṭhaṅgiko maggo (noble eightfold path)&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># ariyo aṭṭhaṅgiko maggo
## sammādiṭṭhi
- right belief
## sammāsaṅkappo
- right intention
## sammāvācā
- right speech
## sammākammanto
- right conduct
## sammāājīvo
- right livelihood
## sammāvāyāmo
- right effort
## sammāsati
- right memory
## sammāsamādhi
- right concentration
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="this-is-not-mine-i-am-not-this-this-is-not-my-essence">This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my essence.&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>netaṁ mama, nesohamasmi, na meso attāti—
evametaṁ yathābhūtaṁ sammappaññāya daṭṭhabbaṁ.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="reference">Reference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/dn22">Mahāsatipaṭṭhānasutta DN 22 PTS 2.290–2.315 PT&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/mn141">Saccavibhaṅgasutta MN 141 PTS 3.248–3.252&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/pli-tv-kd1">Mahākhandhaka Pli Tv Kd 1 PTS 1.1–1.100 P&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Docs: cattāro satipaṭṭhānā</title><link>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/catt%C4%81ro-satipa%E1%B9%AD%E1%B9%ADh%C4%81n%C4%81/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ChristineTham.github.io/buddhavacana/docs/sutta/catt%C4%81ro-satipa%E1%B9%AD%E1%B9%ADh%C4%81n%C4%81/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="cattāri-ariyasaccāni">cattāri ariyasaccāni&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>viharati ātāpī sampajāno satimā vineyya loke abhijjhādomanassaṁ (keen, aware, and mindful, rid of desire and aversion for the world)&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># cattāri ariyasaccāni
## kāye kāyānupassī
- body
## vedanāsu vedanānupassī
- feelings
## citte cittānupassī
- mind
## dhammesu dhammānupassī
- principles
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h3 id="kāyānupassanā">Kāyānupassanā&lt;/h3>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-markmap" data-lang="markmap"># kāyānupassanā
## Kāyānupassanāānāpānapabba
- Mindfulness of Breathing
## Kāyānupassanāiriyāpathapabba
- The Postures
## Kāyānupassanāsampajānapabba
- Situational Awareness
## Kāyānupassanāpaṭikūlamanasikārapabba
- Focusing on the Repulsive
## Kāyānupassanādhātumanasikārapabba
- Focusing on the Elements
## Kāyānupassanānavasivathikapabba
- The Charnel Ground Contemplations
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h4 id="kāyānupassanāānāpānapabba">Kāyānupassanāānāpānapabba&lt;/h4>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-mermaid" data-lang="mermaid">stateDiagram-v2
state bhikkhu &amp;lt;&amp;lt;choice&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
[*] --&amp;gt; bhikkhu
bhikkhu --&amp;gt; araññagato
bhikkhu --&amp;gt; rukkhamūlagato
bhikkhu --&amp;gt; suññāgāragato
araññagato --&amp;gt; nisīdati_pallaṅkaṁ
rukkhamūlagato --&amp;gt; nisīdati_pallaṅkaṁ
suññāgāragato --&amp;gt; nisīdati_pallaṅkaṁ
nisīdati_pallaṅkaṁ --&amp;gt; ābhujitvā_ujuṁ
ābhujitvā_ujuṁ --&amp;gt; parimukhaṁ_satiṁ_upaṭṭhapetvā
parimukhaṁ_satiṁ_upaṭṭhapetvā --&amp;gt; [*]
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="reference">Reference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/dn22">Mahāsatipaṭṭhānasutta DN 22 PTS 2.290–2.315 PT SC&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ancient-buddhist-texts.net/Buddhist-Texts/D22-Mahasatipatthana/index.htm">Mahāsatipaṭṭhānasuttaṁ (DN 22) ABT&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/mn141">Saccavibhaṅgasutta MN 141 PTS 3.248–3.252&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://suttacentral.net/pli-tv-kd1">Mahākhandhaka Pli Tv Kd 1 PTS 1.1–1.100 P&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>